Guide to the Records of the American Art-Union 1838-1860 MS 12
New-York Historical Society
American Art-Union Records
1838-1860
New-York Historical Society
American Art-Union
MS 12
10 Linear feet (109 bound volumes and 1 box on 63 reels of microfilm)
The collection consists of 109 volumes and 1 box of records from 1838 to 1860 of the American Art-Union. Online version available to users affiliated with subscribing institutions via Gale Cengage Learning.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Portions of the collection that have been microfilmed will be brought to the researcher in that format and can be made available by Interlibrary loan.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.) Researchers on site may print out unlimited copies from microfilm reader-printer machines at per-exposure rates. See guidelines in Reading Room for details.
Historical Note
The American Art-Union was known as the Apollo Association for the Promotion of the Fine Arts in the United States.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of 109 volumes and 1 box of records from 1838 to 1860. Volumes include minutes of annual meetings, executive committee, committee of management, and purchasing committee; register of works of art in the American Art-Union, including title of the painting submitted, the artist, price asked, cost of frame and whether or not a picture was purchased or rejected; letters addressed to the American Art-Union, including many from agents around the country, and pertaining to the sale of subscriptions; letters from artists to the American Art-Union with index; letterpress books containing copies of letters sent by the American Art-Union; and newspaper clippings. The box includes photocopies, indices to letters from artists and letters received, as well as two 19th century bindings.
Arrangement
The volumes are arranged chronologically under record type: minutes of annual meeting, 1839-1849 (1 vol.); minutes of the committee of management, 1839-1855 (3 vols.); minutes of the executive committee, 1846-1854 (2 vols.); minutes of the purchasing committee, 1850 (1 vol.); treasurer's accounts, 1849-1860 (1 vol.); register of works of art in the American Art-Union, 1848-1851 (1 vol.); letters addressed to the Art-Union, 1838-1852 (65 vols.); letters from artists to the Union, 1849-1851 (8 vols.); letterpress books, 1843-1852 (25 vols.); and newspaper clippings (2 vols.).
The collection consists of 109 bound volumes and 1 box of records.
Letterpress copybooks.; Copybooks; Letters (correspondence); Price lists; Accessions registers.; Accounts.; Minutes (administrative records); Artists -- United States -- Societies, etc.; Art -- United States.; Art -- United States -- Societies, etc.; Clippings (information artifacts); Bookbinding; Apollo Association for the Promotion of the Fine Arts in the United States
- Microfilm Reel List
  Scope and Contents note
  Following is a listing of the contents of the microfilm reels that contain the material in the box and bound volumes of the American Art-Union collection. Online version available to users affiliated with subscribing institutions via Gale Cengage Learning.
  - Management Committee Minutes, Volumes 1-3, 1839-1855 (Reel 1)
  - Minutes of Annual Meetings, 1839-1850 (Reel 1)
  - Treasurer's Accounts, 1849-1860 (Reel 1)
  - Executive Committee Minutes, Volumes 1-2, 1846-1854 (Reel 2)
  - Registers, Works of Art, 1848-1851 (Reel 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Volumes 1-2 (Reel 3)
  - Purchasing Committee Minutes, 1850 (Reel 3)
  - Letters from Artists, 1848 Nov. 15 -1849 Sept. 28 (Reel 4)
  - Letters from Artists, 1849 Oct. 1-1850 June 28 (Reel 5)
  - Letters from Artists, 1850 July 1- 1850 Dec. 31 (Reel 6)
  - Letters from Artists, 1851 Jan. 1-1851 Dec. 29 (Reel 7)
  - Letters Received, 1838 April- 1843 Jan. 31 (Reel 8)
  - Letters Received, 1843 Feb. 2-1845 April 11 (Reel 9)
  - Letters Received, 1845 Feb. 17-1846 June 22 (Reel 10)
  - Letters Received, 1846 June 22- 1846 Dec.12 (Reel 11)
  - Letters Received, 1846 Dec. 13-1847 June 30 (Reel 12)
  - Letters Received, 1847 July 1- 1847 Nov. 26 (Reel 13)
  - Letters Received, 1847 Nov. 27- 1847 Dec. 31 (Reel 14)
  - Letters Received, 1848 Jan. 1- 1848 May 31 (Reel 15)
  - Letters Received, 1848 June 1-1848 Aug. 31 (Reel 16)
  - Letters Received, 1848 Sept. 1-1848 Oct. 25 (Reel 17)
  - Letters Received, 1848 Oct.26-1848 Nov. 30 (Reel 18)
  - Letters Received, 1848 Nov. 24-1848 Dec. 11 (Reel 19)
  - Letters Received, 1848 Dec. 11-1848 Dec. 31 (Reel 20)
  - Letters Received, 1849 Jan. 1-1849 Apr. 23 (Reel 21)
  - Letters Received, 1849 Apr. 3-1849 June 29 (Reel 22)
  - Letters Received, 1849 July 1-1849 Sept. 24 (Reel 23)
  - Letters Received, 1849 Sept. 26-1849 Nov. 7 (Reel 24)
  - Letters Received, 1849 Nov.8-1849 Nov. 30 (Reel 25)
  - Letters Received, 1849 Dec. 1-1849 Dec. 12 (Reel 26)
  - Letters Received, 1849 Dec. 12-1849 Dec. 19 (Reel 27)
  - Letters Received, 1849 Dec. 19-1850 Mar. 31 (Reel 28)
  - Letters Received, 1850 Apr. 1-1850 May 31 (Reel 29)
  - Letters Received, 1850 June 1-1850 Aug. 15 (Reel 30)
  - Letters Received, 1850 Aug. 16- 1850 Nov. 21 (Reel 31)
  - Letters Received, 1850 Nov. 22-1850 Dec. 16 (Reel 32)
  - Letters Received, 1850 Dec. 12- 1850 Dec. 31 (Reel 33)
  - Letters Received, 1851 Jan. 1-1851 Apr. 21 (Reel 34)
  - Letters Received, 1851 Apr. 22-1851 June 26 (Reel 35)
  - Letters Received, 1851 June 27-1851 Sept. 8 (Reel 36)
  - Letters Received, 1851 Sept. 9-1851 Nov. 30 (Reel 37)
  - Letters Received, 1851 Dec. 1-1851 Dec. 31 (Reel 38)
  - Letters Received, 1852 Jan. 1-1852 Feb. 28 (Reel 39)
  - Letters Received, 1852 Mar. 1-1852 Dec. 31 (Reel 40)
  - Letterpress Books, 1843 Mar. 28-1845 Dec. 31 (Reel 41)
  - Letterpress Books, 1846 Jan. 3-1847 Jan. 6 (Reel 42)
  - Letterpress Books, 1847 Jan. 7-1847 Dec. 18 (Reel 43)
  - Letterpress Books, 1847 Dec. 20-1848 June 7 (Reel 44)
  - Letterpress Books, 1848 June 8-1848 Aug. 30 (Reel 45)
  - Letterpress Books, 1848 Aug. 29-1848 Dec. 8 (Reel 46)
  - Letterpress Books, 1848 Dec. 8-1849 Mar. 26 (Reel 47)
  - Letterpress Books, 1849 Mar. 26-1849 July 11 (Reel 48)
  - Letterpress Books, 1849 July 12-1849 Nov. 5 (Reel 49)
  - Letterpress Books, 1849 Nov. 5-1849 Dec. 14 (Reel 50)
  - Letterpress Books, 1849 Dec. 14-1850 Feb. 12 (Reel 51)
  - Letterpress Books, 1850 Feb. 13-1850 June 4 (Reel 52)
  - Letterpress Books, 1850 June 4-1850 July 29 (Reel 53)
  - Letterpress Books, 1850 July 27- 1850 Nov. 14 (Reel 54)
  - Letterpress Books, 1850 Nov. 14-1850 Dec. 17 (Reel 55)
  - Letterpress Books, 1850 Dec. 17-1851 Feb. 21 (Reel 56)
  - Letterpress Books, 1851 Feb. 21-1851 May 22 (Reel 57)
  - Letterpress Books, 1851 May 23-1851July 11 (Reel 58)
  - Letterpress Books, 1851 July 10-1851 Sept. 30 (Reel 59)
  - Letterpress Books, 1851 Sept. 30-1851 Dec. 11 (Reel 60)
  - Letterpress Books, 1851 Dec. 11-1852 Feb. 9 (Reel 61)
  - Letterpress Books, 1852 Feb. 9-1853 Mar. 22 (Reel 62)
  - Letterpress Books, 1853 Mar. 24-1853 June 26 (Reel 63)